Personal Information

CURRICULUM VITAE Benard Odhiambo Oloo



Current position held: Assistant Lecturer

Employer: Dairy and Food Science and Technology Department, Egerton

University. Box 536-20115

Tel: +254-725-817-520

Email: olooo.odhimabo@gmail.com or benard.oloo@egerton.ac.ke

Summary

Mr. Benard Oloo is a Food Safety and Quality Expert, a team Leader, Lecturer of Food Science, Trainer, Life Coach and Author. Mr. Oloo is a Lecturer of Food science and Technology at Egerton University focusing on Food safety of different commodity value chains in Kenya. He holds an MSc. Food Science and Technology from Egerton and successfully defended his PhD in March 2021 from the same University awaiting degree conferment. Previously, he has worked in the Food Industry both as a production supervisor, production manager and quality assurance manager. He is currently in charge of the Guildford Dairy Institute at Egerton University where he is serving as a Food Safety Team Leader implementing ISO 22000:2005, Food Safety Management System. Mr. Oloo's research include new product development, value addition, quality and safety. Some of the specific commodities he has worked with include fruits and vegetables, milk and milk products, potatoes, sweet potatoes, meat and meat, indigenous chicken products quality and safety. He has earned several international awards including: Borlaug Fellowship (Michigan State University USA 2019), Emerging Leaders Network Award by Institute of Food Technology (IFT), USA 2018, PhD student exchange programme (Durban University of Technology, South Africa) and the African Biosciences Challenge Fund, 2017-2018 at ILRI, Kenya.

Academic Qualifications

Highest Academic qualification: PhD in Food Science

Research area: Design of HACCP system for improved quality and safety of indigenous chicken in Kenya.

2021- PhD Graduate _Successfully defended (awaiting graduation).

Awarding Institution:

Egerton

University

Area of specialization: Food Safety and value addition, HACCP

development, Food Processing and preservation, and Food Biotechnology.

2014 MSc. Food Science

Egerton

University, Kenya

Area of specialization: Enhanced retention of *Beta-carotene* in Orange

Fleshed Sweet potatoes by lactic acid Fermentation.

	2008 BSc. Food Science and Technology (Fisrt class Honours)
	Egerton University, Kenya
Fields of	Food Science, Food safety, Food biotechnology and Value addition
Specialization	
Professional	Food Scientist, Published Author, Editor and Life Coach
qualification	
Work experience	Egerton University
	Year:2014-Date
	Position / Designation: Assistant Lecturer-Food Science and Technology. Conducting research, teaching and examination of Food Science and related courses. Lecturing and taking students through various practical courses in Food Science and related courses.
	Writing multi country & multi-Agency, Fundable research proposals. Editor and reviewer of at least 3 scientific journals. Editor of the GHI Matters from February, 2021. Food Safety Team leader for Guildford Dairy Institute implementing ISO
	22000:2005 food safety management system.
	Egerton University and Eldoret Polytechnique and Jomo Kenyatta
	University of Agriculture and Technology
	Year: 2011-2014
	Position / Designation: Part time Lecturer and Free Lance Writer. Lecturing Technology of Specific Products (meat poultry and sea foods, fruits and vegetables, dairy, cereals and root crops, cereals, root crops and pulses).
	Sparta Food Ltd., Nairobi
	Year: 2010-2011
	Position/designation: -Production Manager Production scheduling and quality control of production of potato chips and other products.
	Njoro Canning Company Ltd, Nakuru
	Year: 2008-2010
	Position/ Designation: Quality Assurance Manager and Food Safety
	Team Leader
	Food Safety Team Leader ensuring production in compliance with HACCP,
TZ D	BRC and IFS, Food Safety Management Systems.
Key Projects	Name of Research Project-PIRA Grant Year: 2021-Member of research team awarded tripartite MSU-EU-SVU_PIRA Grant 2021.
	Name of Research Project: Borlaug Fellowship Year:2019-2020
	Field of Research : Biotechnology: Quality and Safety of GMOs Role played: Researcher (Borlaug Fellow, USA). Status: -ongoing

Name of Research Project: Indigenous chicken Improvement Programme Year: 2014-2020 Field of Research-Quality and Safety of Indigenous chicken (IC) in Kenya and development of HACCP for IC processing. Role Played: Researcher Status: Ongoing. Name of Research: Optimization of Process Condition for fermentation of Orange fleshed sweet potatoes. Year 2008-2014 **Field of Research**: Food Processing and Preservation Role Played: Researcher Status: Completed. 2011-Consultant-Value Lead Project supported by the European Union Documentation of the food industry players in Kenya and the value chains they operate in. Research Improved Food and Nutrition Security by fostering International collaborative research geared to the application of knowledge and Interest experience, and innovative tools in the area of Food science, Food Safety and value addition to guarantee food safety for improved livelihoods and towards poverty alleviation. From Doctoral Dissertation-Publications with peer Review Process **Publications** 1. Benard O. Oloo*, Symon M. Mahungu, Alexander K. Kahi, and Eric Amonsou. (2019). Fatty Acid and Amino Acid Profile of Indigenous Cluster Ecotypes of Kenyan Free-ranging Chicken. Journal of Food and Nutritional Sciences Research 2019, 1(1), 1-11. Available from: https://kifst.org/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/Fatty-Acid-and-Amino-Acid-Profile-of-Indigenous-Cluster-Ecotypes-of-Kenyan-Freeranging-Chicken.pdf 2. **Oloo, B. O.**, Mahungu, S., Kahi, A., & Amonsou, E. (2018). Quantity and Functionality of Protein Fractions Isolated from 3 Ecotypes of Indigenous Chicken in Kenya. Food Science and *Nutrition*, 2(3). For more details click here: DOI: 22158/fsns.v2n3p70 3. Oloo, B. O*., Mahungu, S., & Kahi, A. (2018). Descriptive sensory quality of Kenya's indigenous chicken meat from different ecotypeclusters reared under an intensive system. African Journal of Food, *Agriculture, Nutrition and Development, 18*(1). For more details click here DOI: 10.18697/ajfand.81.16900 4. Oloo B O*, Mahungu S, Gogo L, A Kahi (2017). Design of a HACCP plan for indigenous chicken slaughter house in Kenya. J. Food Agric. Nutr. Dev. 2017; 17(1): 11616-11638 For more details click here DOI: 10.18697/ajfand.77.16765. **Further Publications-with peer review process**

- 1. **Oloo, B***., Maredia, K., & Mbabazi, R. (2020). Advancing adoption of genetically modified crops as food and feed in Africa: The case of Kenya. African Journal of Biotechnology, 19(10), 694-701. For more details click here: DOI: 10.5897/AJB
- 2. **Oloo, B*.**, Maredia, K., & Mbabazi, R. (2020). Earning trust and building credibility with a new paradigm for effective scientific risk-benefit communication of biotechnology innovations. African Journal of Biotechnology, 19(9), 684-693. For more details click here DOI: 10.5897/AJB
- 3. **Benard Oloo***, Lanoi Daisy and Ruth Oniang'o (2018). *Food Safety Legislation in Some Developing Countries*, Food Safety. Yehia El-Samragy, IntechOpen, DOI: 10.5772/intechopen.75587. Available from: https://www.intechopen.com/books/food-safety-some-global-trends/food-safety-legislation-in-some-developing-countries.
- 4. Oloo, B. O.; Oniang'o, R.; Lanoi, D. (2017). Enhancing Global Harmonization of regulations for reducing Food losses and Waste in sub-Saharan Africa. The 1st All Africa Post Harvest Congress & Exhibition, Reducing food losses and waste: sustainable solutions for Africa, 28th-31st March 2017, Nairobi, Kenya. Conference Proceedings 2017 pp.171-172 ref.2 Click here Enhancing global harmonization of regulations for reducing food losses and waste in sub-Saharan Africa, for details.
- 5. Benard Oloo and Julia IJsselmuiden (2016). Reducing World Food Losses: Fresh demo project introduces 'Contronics Humidifiers' solution to agri-food losses. African Journal of Food Agriculture and Nutrition. Afr. J. Food Agric. Nutr. Dev. 2016; 16(4): Commentary. Avialable at: https://www.ajfand.net/Volume16/No4/Commentary-Oloo.pdf
- 6. **Benard OO** (2016) Lessons in Sustainable Dairy Farming to Kenyan Dairy Sector from the Dutch Dairy Sector. J Adv Dairy Res 4: 162. for more details click <u>Lessons in Sustainable</u> Dairy DOI:10.4172/2329-888X.1000162
- 7. **Oloo Benard O***., Shitandi. A., Mahungu S. Malinga J. B, Ogata, B. R. (2013). Effects of Lactic Acid Fermentation on the Retention of B-Carotene Content of Orange Fleshed sweet potato. *International Journal of Food Studies*. Vol. 3: pp. 13-33. For more details click here: DOI 10.7455/ijfs/3.1.2014.a2
- 8. **Oloo Benard O***., Shitandi. A., Mahungu S. Malinga J. B. (2013). Effects of Lactic Acid Fermentation on Sensory Profile of Orange Fleshed Sweet Potato, *Journal of Food and Nutrition Sciences*. 1, No. 1, 2013, pp. 1-5. For more details click here: doi: 10.11648/j.jfns.20130101.13

Publications with peer review as conference proceedings

- Benard Oloo: Emerging food safety concerns even as we celebrate the World Food Safety Day 2020. GHI Newsletter. June, 2020 https://mail.google.com/mail/u/0/#search/GHI+news/FMfcgxwJWXVClzdjQLVnbjqwfpNmHcJC
- 2. **Oloo Benard O.,** Obar James A., Mahungu Symon M., Kahi Alexander K., Machuka Eunice, Rogger Pelle. (2019). Metagenomic Characterization of microbial communities from different nodes of indigenous chicken value chain in Kenya. 1st GHI World Congress on Food Safety and Security held between 23-29th March 2019, Leiden, the Netherlands.
- 3. **Oloo Benard O,.** Mahungu, L. Gogo and A.K. Kahi. (2018). Fatty Acid and Amino Acid Profiles of 3 Cluster Ecotypes of Indigenous Chicken in Kenya. Conference Proceedings of the Egerton University's 12th International Conference from 28th to 30th March, 2018. The theme of the conference is: Knowledge Solutions for the Society, the Economy and the Environment.
- 4. B.O. Oloo, S.M.Mahung, L.A. Gogo, A.K.Kahi, N. Wafula. (2017). Descriptive Sensory Quality of Kenya's Indigenous Chicken Meat from Different Ecotype-Clusters Reared under an Intensive System. Conference Proceedings of the 11th EGERTON UNIVERSITY INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE AND INNOVATION WEEK ON KNOWLEDGE AND INNOVATION FOR SOCIAL AND ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT. HELD BETWEEN 29 TH 31ST MARCH, 2017 FACULTY OF EDUCATION COMPLEX, EGERTON UNIVERSITY, NJORO, KENYA
- 5. Benard Oloo., Daisy Lanoi and Ruth Oniango'. (2017). ENHANCING GLOBAL HARMONIZATION OF REGULATIONS FOR REDUCING FOOD LOSSES AND WASTE IN SUB-SAHARAN AFRICA. Conference Proceedings from the 1st All Africa Post-harvest Congress and Exhibition. Held from 28th-31st of March, 2017 at Safari Park Hotel, Nairobi Kenya.
- 6. **Oloo Benard O*.,** Mahungu, L. Gogo and A.K. Kahi. (2016). *Design of a HACCP Plan for indigenous chicken Slaughter house in Kenya*. Poster presented at 18th World Congress of Food Science and Technology, IUFoST, at Royal Dublin Society, Dublin, Ireland.
- 7. Oloo Benard O,. Mahungu, L. Gogo and A.K. Kahi. (2016). Key note speaker at "ASSURING SAFETY OF KENYAN INDIGENOUS CHICKEN; THINKING GLOBALLY WHILE ACTING LOCALLY". 1st World Congress on Innovations for Livestock Development. Fostering Innovations for the Livestock Industry 26th 30th June, 2016 Sentrim Elementaita Lodge, Nakuru, Kenya.
- 8. **Oloo Benard O,.** Mahungu, L. Gogo and A.K. Kahi. (2015). Prevalence of E.coli, Salmonella, Staphylococcus aureus and coliforms on surfaces and rinse water in poultry slaughter house in

Nakuru County. Presented at Regional conference on SUSTAINABLE IMPROVEMENT OF INDIGENOUS CHICKEN **PRODUCTIVITY** at ARC Hotel, Egerton University from 9th-10th Sept. 2015 9. **Oloo Benard O.**, Kibe Anthony, Ochola Sylvans (2014). Harnessing the Value of Banana as a Strategic Commodity for Increased Competitive Advnatage in Selected Counties in Kenya. Presented at the Fourth Anual International Conerence on Innovations for Advancement of Humanity. IFAH-2014 from 2-4th July, 2014 at Eldoret Polytechnic, Kenya. 1. Dr. Mary OMwamba Nyambeki, Referees Chairperson of Department, Department of Dairy and Food Science and Technology, Egerton University P.O. Box 536-20115, Egerton. 2. Hon. Prof. Ruth K. Oniang'o, PhD Editor-in-Chief, African Journal of Food, Agriculture, Nutrition and Development (AJFAND) Founder, Rural Outreach Program (ROP) Africa. 9 Planets Apartments, Block V2 Kabarnet Gardens, Off Kabarnet Road [Off Ngong Road] P.O. Box 29086-00625 Nairobi, KENYA Cellphone: +254-703 113995. 3. Prof. Alexander K. Kahi (Dr. sc. agr.) | Deputy Vice Chancellor (Academic Affairs). Egerton University, P. O. Box 536, 20115 Egerton, Kenya Tel: +254 51 221 7684/5 | Mobile: +254 72 785 0007 | Fax: +254 51 221 768 International Programmes Director, Department of Animal Sciences, Faculty of Agriculture.